# Filippo Guerranti

## Ph.D. Student in Machine Learning for Graphs

name[dot]surname[at]gmail[dot]com

"You should not allow yourself to be convinced by repeated failures."
R. J. Trudeau

## TL;DR

I am conducting research on *machine learning for graphs*. In particular, my interests lie in how to properly handle the relational structure that may be available for a specific task, how to refine it if it is incomplete or noisy, or how to create a new one if it is absent. I am actively interested in studying how graph neural networks work and how to improve their performance and applicability to real-world scenarios from a theoretical perspective.

#### **EDUCATION**

## Ph.D. in Data Analytics and Machine Learning

June 2022 – Present

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY OF MUNICH

Munich, Germany

- · Research interests: machine learning on graphs, relational learning, reliable machine learning.
- · Advisor: Prof. Dr. Stephan Günnemann.
- · Teaching activities: lecture and exam preparation, practical course and seminars.
- Attendance of courses on technical aspects of machine learning, scientific paper writing, conference presentations, entrepreneurial leadership, and entrepreneurial mindset.

# M.Sc. in Computer and Automation Engineering UNIVERSITY OF SIENA

December 2019 – April 2022

Siena, Italy

- Grade: 110/110 cum laude with Honors (highest possible grade) | GPA: 4.0/4.0.
- Thesis title: "Approximating Logical Reasoning using Neural Networks".
- Supervisors: Prof. Marco Maggini, Prof. Michelangelo Diligenti, Dr. Francesco Giannini, Prof. Edmondo Trentin.
- Major in Artificial Intelligence.

# B.Sc. in Computer and Information Engineering University of Siena

October 2015 – December 2019

Siena, Italy

• Grade: 106/110 | GPA: 3.47/4.0.

- Thesis title: "Software for the automatic generation of the exam date calendar".
- · Advisor: Prof. Marco Maggini.
- Major in Systems and Control.

## High School of Applied Science Diploma

September 2010 – June 2015

ISTITUTO DI ISTRUZIONE SUPERIORE TITO SARROCCHI

Siena, Italy

- Grade: 100/100 (highest possible grade).
- Thesis title: "The double face of progress".
- Class president for three consecutive years.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## Research assistant

June 2022 – Present

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY OF MUNICH (DAML GROUP)

Munich, Germany

- · Chair's head: Prof. Dr. Stephan Günnemann.
- Led and collaborated on various research topics related to graph learning, including learning graph structure and certifying graph neural networks' robustness.
- Utilized deep learning frameworks (e.g., PyTorch, TensorFlow, and JAX) for the implementation and training of neural networks.
- Employed graph learning libraries (e.g., PyTorch Geometric, DGL), and developed custom libraries for machine learning on graphs.
- Planned and scheduled complex experiments on computer clusters via dedicated libraries (e.g., Slurm, Hydra, and SEML).
- Skilled in utilizing both local and cloud-hosted distributed version control systems (e.g., Git, GitHub, and GitLab) for software development and team collaboration.

## Research intern

July 2020 - April 2022

University of Siena (SAILab Group)

Siena, Italy

- · Chair's head: Prof. Marco Gori.
- Conducted research on the application of first-order logic semantics to neural networks via knowledge graphs, knowledge graph embeddings, and relational learning.
- Employed deep learning libraries (e.g., TensorFlow, and Keras) to implement scientific code.
- Participated in seminars about deep learning, learning with constraints, computer vision, bioinformatics, and natural language processing.

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

## Praktikum – Large-Scale Machine Learning

 $March\ 2023-July\ 2023$ 

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY OF MUNICH (DAML GROUP)

Munich, Germany

• Supervision of two groups (six students) on the selected lab projects: (i) Adversarial Robustness of Graph Contrastive Learning Methods, and (ii) Representation Learning and Anomaly Detection on Heterogeneous Graphs (in collaboration with Energy4U).

# Seminar – Selected Topics in Machine Learning Research Technical University of Munich (DAML group)

September 2022 – January 2023 Munich, Germany

• Supervision of three students on the selected topics: (i) Graph Structure Learning, (ii) Graph Contrastive Learning, and (iii) Graph Discovery for Time-Series Data and Interacting Systems.

## WORK EXPERIENCE

## Aptitude Assessment Commission member

June 2022 – Present Munich. Germany

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY OF MUNICH

Responsible for conducting interviews with prospective candidates, and identifying talented and promising individuals with strong foundations in computer science, a passion for innovation, and a dedication
to pursuing advanced studies in the fields of Data Engineering and Analytics, and Informatics.

• Gained experience reviewing resumes and CVs to evaluate the academic and professional qualifications of candidates, and their potential fit for the programs.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

Guerranti, F., & Dimitri, G. M. (2023). A Comparison of Machine Learning Approaches for Predicting Employee Attrition. *Applied Sciences*, 13(1), 267.

Guerranti, F., Mannino, M., Baccini, F., Bongini, P., Pancino, N., Visibelli, A., & Marziali, S. (2021). CaregiverMatcher: Graph neural networks for connecting caregivers of rare disease patients. *Procedia Computer Science*, 192, 1696-1704.

#### INVITED TALKS

## Approximating Logical Reasoning using Neural Networks

February 2022

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY OF MUNICH

Online

• Hosted at the Data Analytics and Machine Learning groupchair, by Prof. Dr. Stephan Günnemann.

## Approximating Logical Reasoning using Neural Networks

March 2022

CISPA HELMHOLTZ CENTER FOR INFORMATION SECURITY

Online

· Hosted at the Trustworthy Information Processing chair, by Prof. Dr. Aleksandar Bojchevski.

## SCHOLARSHIPS & AWARDS

Best Student Award – Computer and Automation Engineering, University of Siena	October 2022
<b>Top 8</b> – Rare Disease Hackathon, <i>PadMatch project</i>	April 2020
Personal grant – Scholarship for part-time student collaboration, University of Siena	March 2018
Personal grant – Scholarship for deserving students, Banca CRAS Siena	July 2015

## **CERTIFICATIONS**

Semi Intensive General English Course Advanced Level, ELC, Sydney, Australia	August 2015
FCE Certificate in English B2, Cambridge English Certificate in ESOL International	May 2015
ECDL Full Standard, Italian Association of Informatics and Automatic Computing	February 2015

#### **MEMBERSHIPS**

## Member of the executive board

February 2021 – April 2022

UDIEMS, USIENA DEPT. OF INFORMATION ENGINEERING AND MATHEMATICS SOCIETY

Siena, Italy

• Organization of seminars and events related to computer science and mathematics for students.

## Computer science author

May 2020 - October 2021

Passaporto Futuro (social media)

Online

• Drafting of web and social articles related to the field of computer science, with particular emphasis on artificial intelligence and machine learning topics.

## LANGUAGES

Italian (mother tongue), English (C1), German (A2), Spanish (A2).

## **SKILLS**

**Programming Languages** Python, C/C++, R, Bash, Prolog, SQL, MATLAB

Packages & Frameworks PyTorch, PyTorch Geometric, TensorFlow, JAX, DGL, Hydra, Slurm,

SEML, Numpy, Scipy, Networkx, PyTorch Lightning, Keras, Matplotlib,

Pandas, Scikit-learn

Software & Tools Git, GitHub, GitLab, LATEX, Visual Studio Code, MS Office

Operating Systems macOS, Linux, MS Windows

## HOBBIES AND INTERESTS

**Sports**: running, snowboarding, swimming, yoga, bouldering, hiking. **Reading**: psychology, phylosophy, science, economy, non-fiction, novel.

Travels: camper van trips, tent camping, backpacking trips.

4